Well, welcome everybody. Welcome to TADWIG 2026 in Oslo.
So very pleased that you've made it.
You may not be so pleased with me afterward, but that's okay. I am accustomed.
Very quickly,
a quick thank you to all of our sponsors, who we will detail at length in a
few moments. I just want to give you a quick lay of the land.
This is what's happening today. We're going to begin with some welcoming and
warm conversation and presentation.
Hugo will give us a formal welcome to Oslo.
The deputy chair, Ellie Saliba, will then take care of some housekeeping issues.
I will excite you beyond imagination with an address after
that. And then we have our three keynote speakers, Tanya, Marit, and
Ramona. At that point, we will have lunch. There will be a coffee break in there.
We're just not going to tell you when it is exactly. We'll surprise you.
And then the afternoon is a taste of TADWIG with Ellie Wallace.
There will be some events after that that we'll tell you about, but this is what
you can look forward to. You can find it in the Whova app if you're curious about
the details and the timing of things.
But just so we can figure out who's here today, we will all be really good at
following instructions, so if you can raise your hand if you traveled here from
somewhere in Norway.
That's good. Yeah, some of you will have to turn your heads to see how many hands
are up. That's great. Thank you for hosting us. We appreciate it very much.
And how about if you traveled from somewhere other than Norway?
So the math is mathing. That's good.
Probably the most important question, how many of you paid an arm and a leg to get
here?
Okay, I'm not expecting as many hands because you probably gave them away.
Okay, good.
How about
people who've been to 10 or more TADWIG meetings?
There are some of you that could probably keep that up if I asked for 20.
See, they're still up in the back. Arthur.
How about how many of you are attending this meeting virtually?
Okay, we're just checking for AI agents.
And the most important question, how many of you are here for the first time?
Awesome.
So thank you very much for coming for your first time.
We have some opportunities for you that Ellie Saliba will detail in a couple of
moments. We will just get right to it.
I'm sorry, I'm not doing a very good job of speaking directly into the mic.
We will just get right to it. I want to welcome Hugo de Boer.
He is the,
make sure I get this right, the director of science and the head of the Department
of Research and Collections and the head of delegation for GBIF Norway, as well as
the vice chair of GBIF Science Committee. So Hugo, welcome.
Do you want this or do you want to stand there?
All right.
There we go. Good morning,
and welcome to Oslo. I'm Hugo, as Dave introduced me.
I'm really glad to welcome you here to Oslo and also to the University of Oslo.
And it's a real pleasure for me to open TADWIG.
So
you're looking here at four versions of Edvard Munch's "The Scream,"
one of Norway's great treasures, first dated to
1893. And there's four of us locally who are helping to
organize the meeting, Dag, Rukia, Kathy, and me.
TADWIG, of course, runs the conference.
But getting this many people into the city, keeping the logistics moving, well,
what can I say? This existential panic depicted by Munch in The Scream is something
we could really resonate with at times.
Now look at the walls around you,
because you're sitting inside one of Munch's most ambitious projects.
It's prestigious. It was also a bit controversial in its day.
Munch painted these paintings here in this room more than 100 years ago.
There are 11 paintings, and they tell the story of the university
and the sciences. Behind The Scream is the image of the sun.
It symbolizes enlightenment as a sunrise.
On that wall, we have history with an old man explaining something to
a young boy.
On the left, we see alma mater,
the nourishing university,
reaching back to Bologna's Alma Mater Studiorum from 1088.
And also, I think relevant for us, some of the sciences are also directly
referenced.
We have
over there in the corner is chemistry.
Here
in this corner, we have
physics symbolized by the rays,
and maybe my favorite, we have here
botany,
these women harvesting from the tree of knowledge.
So something about the room itself, the aula, this space is, I think everybody
agrees in Oslo, that this is one of the most beautiful places to be.
The other most beautiful place is the Oslo City Hall,
where the Nobel Peace Prize is awarded each December.
And that is exactly where we will gather this evening at 5:00 for the welcome
reception. So in a single day, you get to stand in both.
Not a bad way, I think, to start the conference.
Our logo is a smiling troll,
which takes us from Munch to Norse mythology,
and to something surprisingly close to what we're working on.
In old Norse sources, trolls dwell in the wild,
isolated places,
mountains, rocks, caves, forests.
They live in small family groups, and they're rarely helpful to humans.
They belong to nature, and they're out at the edge of the known world.
And here we see
Kittelsen and the Norwegian troll.
For over a century, our mental image of the Norwegian troll has been that
created by Theodor Kittelsen. He illustrated the folk tales of
Asbjørnsen and Moe for nearly 30 years, and many say that he
settled once and for all what a Norwegian troll looks like.
And it's that connection
that I want to draw here again to TADWIG, because before Kittelsen, the troll
was in a way formless. Everyone pictured it differently.
But he gave it a shared form. He gave it a kind of common language. Right?
And this is exactly I would say that we're doing here at TADWIG.
Biodiversity, like a troll, is wild, scattered, endlessly varied, and hard to
pin down. Our task here as a group is to give it a shared language,
standards that let data from a forest in Uganda and a specimen drawer
here in Oslo
speak to one another.
We in Norway like to think we live close to nature.
We build our stories around it, and data standards are simply
how we turn that wild, tangled diversity into something we can share, connect, and
protect.
So let us go from trolls to living nature.
The image here on the screen is the University of Oslo's Botanical Garden, Norway's
oldest. It was founded in 1814 and is part of the Natural History Museum.
We have around 5,000 plant species cared for through research, education,
and conservation. The conference itself is here and also at the Congress Center,
but as a host, I would like you to also enjoy the botanical garden.
So if you have time, please do come and explore the wonderful garden while you're
here.
A little bit more history,
and also a personal invitation.
The main wing of Tøyen Manor in the botanical garden is probably the oldest
standing timber building in Greater Oslo.
This house dates to 1679,
and it is an estate that passed through Norway's Chancellor Jens Bjelke, then to
the Danish king, and it was later donated to the university in 1812.
Today, it holds exhibitions and a cafe. It also happens to be where my office is.
So if you're in the garden, do drop by.
A few practical things, instead of all my meanderings about trolls and
folklore.
Wednesday is our day for excursions and also the BioBlitz.
We have forests and lake hikes, island hopping on fjords, birding,
behind-the-scenes visits to our museum and collections.
If you'd like to join, sign up at the registration desk.
Cathy, whom you will have seen here, has the sheets on Tuesday at the Congress
Center. And do join the BioBlitz that we have set up for the meeting on
iNaturalist. We can get some real records recorded in the very
standards that this meeting wants to have.
Wednesday evening,
our conference social. Yesterday, we already had a conference social, but on
Wednesday evening, another conference social, because we're a very social bunch, is
at the Munch Museum on the waterfront. Ninety rooms of Munch.
So if you haven't seen enough Munch, there's more Munch there.
Your ticket that you got, the little sticker, it will get you into the galleries
before and after, so give yourself some time to wonder and enjoy his art.
If you plan to visit several museums and ride the public transport, you can get 20%
off on the Oslo Pass, and I think Cathy also has a code, and you can also email the
conference organizers.
So wrapping up,
this is a little insider tip.
It's something that's happening this very week that goes beyond the usual
highlights. So on Thursday evening, the 24th of September, from 8:00 to
11:00, the electric lights along the Akerselva River that
runs from the mountains through the city to the sea, they are switched off, and
they are replaced by 4,500 torches.
And this whole eight-kilometer route,
with little waterfalls and
streams, comes alive with live performances, music, dance, lights.
It's called the Akerselva Along the River, and the idea is the symbolism of
the autumn equinox, so the balance of light and dark.
So if you have the evening free on Thursday, do consider to visit.
So that's all that I wanted to share with you, and again, welcome to Oslo.
Thank you very much, Hugo. I appreciate that.
Now I would like to introduce to you the deputy chair of TIDWEG, Elie Saliba.
Hi, everybody. So now we're going to look a little bit at the housekeeping for the
week, all the information that you might need to get around.
It's going to be a little bit less poetic than what we've had until now.
But first, to start, I would like to give a huge thanks to the conference committee
and the people who have been working tirelessly to make this happen.
So please, all of you that are in this room, can you stand up so that people can
see you?
And if you have any questions during the week, you can come and find us, all the
people that are here, the picture here.
And
please, so that people can see you, please stand up and be recognizable.
Also, a huge thanks to Kate Louwers and Laura Slaughter, who have also been helping
and working hard to make this happen.
The local team, the Norwegian, have been absolutely incredible, doing everything on
time so that everything can be perfect for you.
And also, all the volunteers who help with the abstract reviews and the TIDWEG
regulars we can count on to make anything happen every year.
So again, thank you to all of these people who have been working to make this
happen. Thank yous also go to our sponsors, GBIF, Bectere, Biosphere Digitation,
Atlas of Living Australia, Pensoft, and EarthGate for their financial help and to
have made all of this happen. You will be able to find their stands during the week
in the foyer of the
Congress Center.
You have the registration stand. I think most of you went through it.
This is where you can get your tickets.
If you have any questions, you can go ask a question there.
For the Congress Center, the stand will be in the foyer.
You already have a map in Whova if you need to find where the foyer is, but it's
basically at the entrance of the building.
If you haven't gotten your T-shirts, they are available there, and if you want to
buy one, you can still buy one
at the registration stand. Also, if you have any questions for, as Hugo just said,
for the excursions, you can ask them or sign up at the registration stand.
For the code of conduct, by being here, you agree to follow the code of conduct.
If you see anything that is out of the ordinary, you
can refer to the code of conduct people.
They can be recognized by a pink star and an orange and brown ribbon around their
neck.
Just please do also be aware that you shouldn't be taking pictures of people
without their consent and publishing them online.
We are in Europe, but also this is just not a nice thing to do.
And so if you need more information about the code of conduct, you can find them on
the link below.
For the Wi-Fi code, because we are all workaholics, we cannot stop checking our
emails every five minutes.
Here in this building, you can use eduroam if you need to.
There's also a password that I cannot say out loud or put on this presentation for
security reasons, but it's on Whova.
So you can go to the
section on Whova about logistics, and you'll find the password for the Wi-Fi, and
you can also request it either from one of the organizers if you don't have any way
to connect or the registration stand.
For tomorrow, the password will be available at the Congress Center, so we have a
way of probably printing it and putting it everywhere, so you'll find it.
Don't worry about this.
If you haven't uploaded your presentation yet, please do.
Don't wait to the last minute to have it
in the Google Drive. The conference program, if you need to
reach for it, is on Whova and on the TIDWEG website.
And if you want, you can download the Whova app to access it on your phone.
A small important thing about the Whova app, if you are on the Whova app, you can
access the posters in the Home section in that menu in particular.
And please keep an eye on the organizers' announcements, because if anything
happens, it's going to be posted there before anywhere else.
In case of an emergency, you can call all of these number, 113 for general help or
for health-related issues, 112 for the police, 110 for fire emergency.
And you can download an app also if you have any reasons that it's easier for you
to
use an app rather than calling. And you can have more information about emergencies
in Norway in the two links that are there.
Obviously, the whole presentation is going to be put on Whova for you to access.
For coffee and lunch breaks, because we all need sugar
to be able to survive this week, so today we're going to be eating in the seller.
I'm not going to try to pronounce this, otherwise I'll lose all my welcome in
Norway.
So this means the aula seller, and it's going to be
in the basement or a couple of stairs below.
There you can scan this QR code to have a map to help guide you, but otherwise you
can just follow the organizers. For the Congress Center, it's going to be upstairs
on the third floor. And it's going to be tables and sitting down lunch.
Today we're having sandwiches.
So on Tuesday in particular, please find Ellie Wallace if you're a newcomer because
we will be hosting a newcomer table so that people for whom it's the first TADWIG,
they can get together,
have a chat, and ask any questions they need to ask to know more about the
community.
If you are in need of accessibility accommodations, here there's an accessible
bathroom directly next to the place we're going to eat.
There's a lift to get you there. In the Oslo Congress Center, the accessible
bathroom is on the first floor next to the cloakroom.
There's also a lift to take you to the third floor if necessary.
Please give priority to people who need it for the use of the lift and use the
stairs if you can.
For the mayor invitation today, so it's at 5:00 PM as Hugo just said, please
have your invitation, the small paper that you have with you, at any time because
there's very strict security measures as it's a public building.
And arrive a little bit earlier because there might be airport-type security to get
in, so a little bit of a queue. So if you can arrive a little bit early to be able
to get in. Some refreshment will be served, no more.
For excursions, again, you can check the details on the website, and if you have
any questions, you can ask the people at the registration desk.
At the Munch Museum,
there will be, as Hugo also just said, a social event.
You can get in basically any time during the day with the other ticket you were
given at the registration desk. There will be a little bit of finger
food and a couple of drink per person. However, the museum closes at 9:00 PM.
And as you might have noticed if you have been here for a couple of days,
restaurants tend to close fairly early.
So if you want to have a real dinner, we advise you to leave a little bit early to
have the time to go to a restaurant and have a little bit of food.
Otherwise, we hope you will enjoy your time at the Munch Museum.
On Thursday, there will be a game night if you wish.
And this is
by TADWIG member for TADWIG members, so people came in with their own games.
It's going to be at the Botanical Garden at the museum, and it's to the Lids house
at the Botanical Garden. So the people who were at the
icebreaker yesterday, it's around 100 meters from where we were yesterday.
Bring your own snacks and drink if you want to participate, and there's also here a
QR code with the map if you need to find your way.
On Friday, there will be our traditional unconference from 1:00 PM to 3:00 PM with
here a list of organizers.
Don't hesitate to reach out to them if you
have any question.
So basically, for the people who do not know, an unconference is an occasion for
you to put forward a subject, something that has been discussed during the week
that you would wish to go deeper into it, or another subject that has not been
mentioned during the week that you would like to see discussed.
And you can scan this QR code to add to the list of topics
that you would like to discuss. Again, all of this is going to be available on
Whova for you to be able to have access
to everything.
And the last part, and another tradition of TADWIG, the BioBlitz is already open.
There are two BioBlitzes, at least in parallel, one for the people here in Norway,
one for our colleagues online worldwide.
So again, you can scan the QR codes to access the BioBlitz and add your pictures
during the week. There will be on Friday the
traditional also BioBlitz review.
So yeah, that's all about Blitz. Just before finishing, Friday will also be the
time for the TADWIG business meeting. We invite you to join if you can.
This is where we discuss the affairs of TADWIG and how
it's managed. And if you have at any time during the week you feel like talking to
people from the exec, if you have questions about how it works, please do not
hesitate to reach for us and ask us any questions you might have.
With this, in the name of all the organizing committee, I bid you welcome to
Norway, and we hope that you're going to enjoy your week and this year's TADWIG.
Thank you very much.
All right.
I think we're in good shape.
Famous last words.
Before I move ahead with my presentation, one clarification.
With game night, it's not just TADWIG members.
Anybody who's here can attend, and we encourage you to do that.
But if you're a member, we'll actually let you sit in a chair.
So have your membership card ready and at hand.
Also, just one quick announcement before I begin.
Every year, as we plan these meetings, somebody sort of
rises to the occasion and becomes a bit of a superhero for the way that these
meetings get planned.
So I'm going to ask a strange question for this crowd because I know who you are.
How many of you are planning to go out for a beer at some point this week?
Okay.
Stan, could you stand up for a second?
Stan is our superhero this year for the meeting.
I hope, Stan, that you took notes on who raised their hands because all of you owe
him a beer.
That's where I'm going with that.
Already, he has saved the day, and we're only 30 minutes in.
So
superhero Stan, just
pay him all due respect.
So I forgot to do this at the beginning. I'm Dave Bloom.
I'm the chair of TADWIG, and I welcome you once again to
TADWIG 2026 here in Oslo.
I'd like to take, if I could, the next 90 minutes to talk with you all about the
great things that TADWIG is doing and all the challenges that we face.
Unfortunately for me, but very fortunate for you, Ellie Wallace, who put
together the program, knows all too well that I am more than capable of talking
about TADWIG for 90 minutes, and so she said I could have 15.
So rather than sulk over this crushing defeat, I have decided to make the most of
the 14 minutes that I have remaining and let you know what's going on.
So I'll begin with some of TADWIG's highlights since we were together last.
So perhaps nothing that happened over the last year held the attention of our
communities more than the Darwin Core data package, which I am happy
to say has been ratified
We are grateful to the many people who participated in that multi-year effort,
especially those folks working on the Darwin Core maintenance group.
And you can say yay or cheer for that if you want to do. Thank you.
Hallelujah.
Also in here, they've completed one round of public review, which is intended to
happen three or four times annually. So that was successful.
Now, the biodiversity data quality interest group is moving forward
towards a ratification. They have yet to complete their public review, and that
will be coming up soon.
The minimum information about a digital specimen or MIDS standard
is also poised to enter the public review phase of its journey very soon,
possibly this week, maybe next week. It's going to happen really soon.
And many thanks to both of those groups of people for pushing those processes
forward. A special thanks to Doug Anderson and Sharon Grant, who are the review
managers for both of those standards
respectively. And then finally, the second Darwin Core public review of this
year has been completed. That was just last week.
And all of the proposals reviewed have been passed.
Once those updates and additions have been approved by the executive committee, you
will all see significant changes to the Humboldt extension and to the new
mineralogy extension. All good news.
So this last spring marked another successful round of our virtual working
sessions. Our thanks to past tag chair Ben Norton, and North America regional
representative Erica Krimmel for all of their efforts to make that event work
beautifully. We also have a new task group in our midst, the Image
Quality and AI Readiness Group. So if you are interested to join that effort,
please find Yasin Vakis and Hank Bart during the week, and ask them about
how that's going to work. The TDWG Community Support Fund handed out
four awards this year totaling a little more than 15,000 US dollars.
Those went to mineralogy, sensitive species, invasive species in the environmental
samples, and eDNA working groups.
Some of you may have heard about a small gathering that we held in the fall of last
year in Bogota, Colombia. Living Data 2025 played host to more than
900 participants, including more than 700 in person.
Our thanks to our partners at the Humboldt Institute, GBIF, OBIS, and GeoBon for
making that a meeting to remember.
Stay tuned for more news about the Living Data series.
That'll come a little bit later this week.
We also await word from the EU regarding the recent submission of the Bicycle AI
grant. Meanwhile, our friends at Disco have received a capacity enhancement grant
from GBIF to develop a plan to map their data to the Darwin Core data package, and
we look forward to working with both of those projects.
Finally, Biodiversity Information Science and Standards, that's TDWG's journal and
hosted by Pensoft, has a shiny new editor-in-chief, Ellie Wallace.
Ellie, you want to say hi?
So Ellie has got her work cut out for her, and she plans to refresh the editorial
boards. And she also plans to expand business publishing to include peer-reviewed
papers, of which we already have several manuscripts in the pipeline, which is
great. So please keep us in mind the next time that you have a paper of your own
ready to go to publication. We're also considering, although we haven't decided
yet, on the possibility of discounts to TDWG members for those publication fees.
And just by the way, Ellie is looking for a co-editor for this year's
collection of extended abstracts from this meeting.
So if you're interested in that opportunity or interested in any of the other items
I mentioned about this, please seek out Ellie and talk to her about what is
possible and what kinds of assistance you could use.
So,
that's a nice assortment of good news from TDWG, but there's also more.
So recently, a variety of new communities that are eager to publish their data to
GBIF and other data aggregators have brought a wide range of new data types and
considerations into the TDWG's orbit.
Almost all of these highlights that I just mentioned are examples of how TDWG is
working to meet those needs and the challenges of this community.
As a result, TDWG finds itself at a crossroads of sorts.
We need to think carefully about which path we take to serve our growing community.
So I'd like to take the next couple of minutes and explain how we got here, and
it's my hope that what we can do is find a way to help you help us
to stay on the right path.
So in the 1980s, when TDWG was founded, that's a photograph from the 1980s.
The purpose was to explore taxonomy.
That was the primary focus, and understandably, at the time, participants tended to
be taxonomists, mostly botanists, and academics interested in names.
At the time, communication was limited to handwritten or typed correspondence and
through the mail, I know,
and telephone calls. And the TDWG meetings, such as they were, tended to be the
only opportunity for our community to get together to discuss work in person.
At the time, telephones were just as likely to be used as weapons of murder in
Alfred Hitchcock films as much as they were for communication, and the desktop
machines that we were using at the time were truly personal computers.
The hot topics of discussion, hold onto your seat, were the isolated relational
databases that people were learning how to develop at the time.
Then one day, lightning struck,
and we found ourselves on the cusp of something revolutionary.
So this is a paragraph from some correspondence that TDWG's deputy chair, Eli
Saliba, discovered in a box under a cavernous desk at a botanic garden somewhere in
Belgium while practicing his Indiana Jones cosplay.
The good news is that TDWG, this person, and others understood the value of the
witchcraft that we now know to be the internet, and soon afterward, the next age of
TDWG was upon us.
So TDWG pivoted, and the focus became primary biodiversity data or occurrence data
around the turn of the century. It even sounds old when we say around the turn of
the century. It was a time when those data that were living in isolated relational
databases started to come of age and wanted to get out of the house and away from
their parents. Soon, those data found data portals such as GBIF and the Vertebrate
Networks, both of which I will add are celebrating their 25th anniversaries this
year. Those portals then evolved into places where the data could hang out,
socialize, and be themselves.
New communities of practice arrived at the party, so new tools, formats, and
standards were needed to meet that demand.
XML, RDF, data schemas were all applied, and data standards such as
ABCD and Darwin Core were born. A new focus on ontology to standardize vocabularies
blossomed, and new telecommunications tools like Skype or Zoom changed the way that
we work together, and even our annual meetings begin to evolve into joint ventures
that were of interest to diverse communities all around the globe.
Which leaves us today on the cusp of a new focus for TDWG, linked open data.
This game has already begun. Data package standards for cam traps and Darwin Core
allow us to bring even more communities of practice and new data types into the
TDWG fold,
along with all the associated challenges and
questions about implementation and participation.
So while we can still visit our favorite data portals to discover and access
primary
biodiversity data, we now must find ways to link distributed data resources in ways
that encourage even greater discovery.
So this leaves TDWG with a variety of opportunities and challenges before it.
And thanks to Ellie Wallace, I have time to mention only a few of those most
pressing.
So let's begin with documentation.
We can view this in several ways, but the two most pressing are how we handle our
archives and how we address distributed storage.
For TDWG, archival storage includes those musty boxes of handwritten documents, as
well as all of the digital documents that many of you have created and have hidden
away in your own personal cloud storage accounts.
Also included in our archival storage
is the documentation that we put online to describe and explain our data standards,
our extensions, schemas, and data structures.
In all cases, we need to do some housekeeping, and we need to make some important
decisions about how our tools and documentation can be made more accessible to a
wider audience. In the very near future, we'll be launching a new task group to
review the tools and processes that we use to ensure that we can maintain the
standards that we have and support future standards that may require new and
different forms of documentation.
So participation is another challenge for TDWG, and we want and need each and every
one of you to help us move forward. But to make this happen, TDWG needs to be
better about helping those people who are interested to find a place in TDWG where
their skills and knowledge can be most beneficial.
One way that you can participate is by running for a seat on the TDWG
Executive Committee. This year, there are multiple seats that are up for election.
If you're not feeling ready to jump into an election, then we would love for you to
join one of our subcommittees. The skills that we need on these committees are
vast. They're almost as vast as the number of salmon that you saw in our previous
housekeeping presentation.
And finally, you can join one of our working groups.
All of the maintenance groups, the interest groups, the task groups can use new
perspectives, creative solutions, and extra hands for support.
Now, lest you think that you don't have what it takes to participate in TDWG,
please allow me to share the small subset of the skills and knowledge bases that we
would love to have at every level of the organization.
And I'm not joking about any of those.
It doesn't matter if you're a student or a grizzled old-timer, we'd love to have
you. It also doesn't matter if you are an expert in any given subject or not.
Join us if you have the expertise, and join us if you'd like to learn and acquire
the same expertise for yourself. So please use this week to talk with members of
the executive committee, myself, Ellie especially.
Talk to the chairs of the subcommittees.
Talk to the conveners and members of the task groups and working groups, and find
out how you can become a part of the solutions to our next set of challenges.
Everybody read it? Peter Desmet, you found yours in there, I hope.
Okay. So TDWG is a 100% volunteer organization.
Everyone who works on behalf of TDWG does so because they believe in TDWG's mission
and the role that it plays in science, policy, and education.
Of course, we know that some people are paid indirectly by employers who allow some
people to spend some of their working hours on TDWG business, while others may get
paid for a limited time by special project funding.
But mostly, people are involved with TDWG because they are, at least while we're
here in Norway, altruistic trolls.
And I'm talking about good trolls, I'm not talking about the trolls on the
internet. But even altruistic trolls eventually step away, and when they do, we
need to be sure that they've had a chance to share what they know with the next
generation of trolls. The growth of standards and extensions have created a growing
need for people to help with maintenance, too.
What was once a task that could be completed by one or two people now require four
or five.
This presents an opportunity for TDWG especially to work more closely with its
partners and organizations that we work with often, like GBIF and OBIS, to
imagine how we can maintain these standards more equitably and sustainably.
We also need to broaden our financial outlook and have already begun to explore
ways that we can expand our abilities to support our efforts financially through
partnerships and other forms of giving.
And some of you may have already noticed that the menu items on the TDWG website
have changed. Our treasurer, Chanda Earle, decreed that
she would have a donate button. So soon after her declaration, a miracle occurred,
and we discovered that a donate button had appeared, and it's been used.
Thank you very much, Deb Paul.
Yeah.
So we hope that all of you will be a little more like Deb in that regard, and we
would welcome your participation and ideas on all of these topics.
And there's this other matter. There's a disturbance in the Force.
We've been discussing it for a couple of years now, and in that very short time,
the abilities and applications of artificial intelligence have expanded
exponentially. Is this another revolutionary lightning strike? How will we use it?
What does it mean for our community?
How much and how rapidly will it change how we work?
One thing is certain, the use of AI makes the work of TDWG even more important.
So I encourage all of you to take some time this week to think about these
challenges and how they affect your own work and how they affect the work of your
projects and your institutions.
Take advantage of the fact that there are more than 350 like-minded individuals
here this week in person. Engage with these folks, and engage with the folks that
are watching from their offices and their homes online.
And most importantly, talk to somebody about TDWG and find out how you can make
this community even stronger, more nimble, and resilient.
So with that,
I now will transition to our first keynote speaker.
And I am very pleased
to have the honor to introduce Dr. Tanya Berger-Wolf.
Tanya is a professor of computer science engineering, electrical and computer
engineering, and evolution, ecology, and organismal biology at--
Okay, hold on. Let
me rephrase that. Tanya is a professor of practically everything-
... at The Ohio State University, where she is also the director of the
Translational Data Analytics Institute.
A pioneer in AI for ecology, biodiversity, and conservation, she leads the
NSF-funded Imagin-- I can't say that word.
I've been practicing this for six months, and I still can't say that word.
So Image-Omics, is that right? Image-Omics Institute, and the
US-Canada co-funded AI and Biodiversity Change Global Centre.
Please help me to welcome Tanya, and we welcome her with open
arms.
Thank you. Am I on?
Okay. Clearly, the first order of business is to practice the word Image-Omics.
So among all the titles and icons, my goal for the next about 40 minutes
is to... Ready? Yes. Okay...
is to explain those icons. So
most of the work that I will show is represented in there, and so that is
funded by Image-Omics Institute.
We envision this as the new field of science where we're focused on omics
biology, particularly observable traits and phenotype from images, hence image
omics. And there are two ways to say it, image-omics or imageomics.
Choose your own, and let's practice. So image-omics.
Now you can tell everybody about it.
The US and Canada co-funded AI and Biodiversity Change Global Center, the
NSF funded Institute for Computational Cyber Infrastructure
in the environment for-- sorry. Cyber Infrastructure for Computational Learning in
the Environment, ICICLE, and the newly funded NSF project on
AI-ready biodiversity change global-- sorry, AI-ready biodiversity and
ecology data infrastructure. So, with that, let's get going.
Because this is the opening, right? So we've got to get the energy.
And also, this is my first ADWIC, so I'm super excited to join
this community.
Please be kind.
If you have rotten tomatoes to throw at me while I'm giving this talk, put them
nicely on the stage.
So
why?
We just mentioned AI has come to everything, including to science, and that has
changed also data and conversations about science. But has it?
So going back to kind of the formalization of the scientific method
over a century ago by Henri Poincaré who wrote this
wonderful, very thin book I highly encourage you, called Science and Method, which
he ends with this following paragraph, that scientific method consists in
observation and experiment, duh.
If the scientist had an infinity of time at his disposal, all he had
to do, it would be sufficient to say to him, look, and look carefully.
But since he has now time to look at everything, and above all, to look carefully,
and, something I tell my students all the time, since it is better not to look at
all than to look carelessly, he's forced to make a selection. Right?
And so this is where I would argue technology and computation comes in.
What it brings to the scientific conversation, it doesn't change the scientific
method, but it allows scientists to look at more things more carefully, at larger
scale and higher resolution. Right?
And
we have been developing the technology for scientists to look
at more things over the last 20 years with explosion of remote sensing satellites,
autonomous vehicles underwater, on the ground, and in the air.
The on-body sensors that you can put on animals now as tiny as butterflies.
We're now tracking monarch flight with a sensor that is about three rice grains
size.
These stationary sensors, camera traps, acoustic recorders, and these guys that
now everybody's going to use to add to the iNaturalist.
How many of you have taken a picture of a living organism in the last two days?
This is the right community.
For those who haven't raised their hand, may I also remind you that humans are
indeed living organisms.
Okay. And eDNA and many other sensors.
I just learned about a chemical sensor that can sense the change in phenology of
plants. So there is
ground-penetrating radars that
can start sensing tiny invertebrates.
So the future continues to give us more
things to look at. But can we look at them more carefully? Well, let's see.
First of all, we're done with data, right? We really have everything we need.
All right. Well, so the bottom left, the pointer here, you can barely see it.
Top right left is the biodiversity heat map of the world, and
of course, the Amazon is where it's at.
It's also where we're losing biodiversity the fastest.
You can have essentially the same map for where we're losing biodiversity the
fastest. The bottom left is GBIF observations, the number of GBIF
observations. And really you're starting to see the near complementarity of
where we have highest biodiversity to where we have data on that biodiversity.
The same trends hold for iNat and for eBird, despite the fact that
birders are crazy and will contribute to bird observations wherever they are.
Clearly not everywhere. And so, the thing is that
there's clear geographic bias there in where we actually have data.
But anything you put on the X-axis, if the Y is the number of
observations, whether it's the
species, we're going to have super skewed distributions.
We know a lot about very little, very few species, very few locations,
and then diminishingly nothing about the rest. Right?
In fact, the bias is not just geographic.
There are people who have dug deeper into it, and not surprisingly,
there is a strong correlation by number of observation and the average income per
unit of space. Right? So we have data not where the biodiversity, not where
nature is, but where rich humans are.
That's essentially it. So we still need to get more data.
But can we look at it more carefully?
And so over the last
decade, more now, we also have seen an explosion in computational approaches and
methods to start processing that data, particularly image data, and then more
recently, language data. Right? We can take complex images and start
extracting all the
living organisms are, including humans, where
to do localization, we can put bounding boxes around them, the pose estimation.
We can start naming species. We can reconstruct the environment. Right?
But we still have lots of gaps. So we recently published this paper
on the shortfalls. So we didn't identify the shortfalls of biodiversity data.
That was done previously. But
how
we can not only fill these shortfalls, but it's a prospective paper.
What role and potential do AI methods play in filling those shortfalls,
and what needs to be done to develop those AI methods?
Because many of them still do not exist. And this is where my job starts.
But okay, if you look at these shortfalls, starting with Linnaean, this bold
taxonomic naming and description, this group should know the answer.
How many estimated species of
plants, fungi, and animals are out there about?
20 million. Huh?
Really? Okay, come on. Order of magnitude.
10 million. 10 million. All right.
So up until about four years ago, right, the estimate was somewhere around 10, 15
million. And about four years, because it's based on the rate of discovery, and we
started discovering species a lot faster, especially in the ocean, the number has
jumped to about 30 to 50 million estimated species out there.
But we still have only about two million, right, named.
And even that is argued that they're duplicates, so maybe it's just a million and a
half. But the gap is growing. So this shortfall, the
Linnaean shortfall, that is probably the kind of-- this is the community to fill
it. That gap is growing, not shrinking.
And then in the order, we see the estimating abundance,
the
distribution information, regional distribution space, so that's the spatial, the
responses to the environment, morphology and function of organisms, the traits
particularly, and then putting it in the context of phylogeny, and then the last
one is on interactions. And so we see that this goes from just naming things to
increasingly complex structure
of biological systems. Right?
Because nothing makes sense except in the context of environment and evolution.
And so great, this covers pretty much all of ecology, all of
that part of science.
So what does AI have to do with this?
For every single one of them, not only are there existing ways,
existing methods that we can use to fill those shortfalls,
but they all link on the right to the state-of-the-art and the
very active research in AI. But to do this, to actually develop these
methods in machine learning, in AI... And when I say AI, I do not mean LLMs.
Most of it, 99%, is machine learning.
And so
a lot of the work is happening within the machine learning community,
which is very exciting when you publish good ground-truthed
datasets with beautiful pictures of birds,
and good well-defined computational tasks.
We call them benchmarks in the machine learning community. Here's a large dataset.
Here's the well-defined computational task.
Here's the baselines on other methods that exist out there that how they perform on
that task. Ready, set, go. And the entire machine learning community goes, set,
go... Well, not entire, but a good number goes to competition.
Just for comparison, machine learning conferences these days, or related all of the
AI machine learning conferences, are about 20,000 to 25,000 people,
right? So that community, even a fraction of it, when they get excited about these
problems, things happen. But the thing is that the way we solve it right now also
has to change, because quite often we come out with methods that have very little
impact or relevance to the original problem that's been posed, right?
Because they are very benchmark oriented, and the benchmarks and the accuracy
methods drive the solutions that give you better and better answers about the bulk
of the very skewed distribution, where we have a lot of data, where we already know
everything we wanted to know about.
And so we keep on getting to know more things about the things that we already know
everything we wanted to know about, not that long tail
where the discovery is hidden, where the new things are, where we do need
desperately to find
ways to understand something about it, right?
So if we do want to look at these things more carefully, we need AI that makes that
discovery possible, that is interpretable, and that generates testable hypotheses.
Right? So that's a paper. I'm not a coauthor, but it's a wonderful paper that was
published by my colleagues, including Sarah Beery.
And so we said, okay, well, for that, we need to actually incorporate biological
knowledge into
the design of these methods. And that was the goal of
the big project from the Image Genomics Institute.
And by the way, Hilmar Labbé and Yasin Bakkies and Heng Bart, who's hiding over
there,
are all a part of the Image Genomics Institute and are here.
With that, the simplest, dumbest way, right, the most immediate way to incorporate
biological knowledge into design of machine learning methods.
So we said, okay, we're going to design a foundation model, build a foundation
model for organismal foundation model from images,
by just adding taxonomy, the full taxonomic sequence, as a caption to every image.
That's it, right? Does it give us anything?
And so we trained the foundation model on the
version two is 214 million images
of about a million species. So that's half of everything that's named out there.
That brings up that it evens out the taxonomic bias a little bit, because we
have
brought up the insects and invertebrates in general quite a bit up in that
dataset. So it comes from Encyclopedia of Life, GBIF.
iNat, we did a lot of deduplication.
FathomNet, which is a great dataset
and a great organization in general that's focused on making marine and ocean data,
image data,
AI-ready. And then BioSCAN, which is the project on developing
DNA barcodes for species, but they also photograph all the
samples that they derive the DNA samples from, the species.
And so that together, we build this model, BioCLIP, and it
implicitly learns the taxonomy. Great. Amazing.
So you can do it not just to species, whatever you want to do, not just to species,
but to any taxonomic level. And because it's a foundation model,
we didn't train it to do species classification.
We just labeled the images with that. But it does learn species.
It can do species classification because it learned to associate names with images.
But wait, there's more. It can do many other things. So scale matters, turns out.
The information contained in images sub-partition the clusters within every
species cluster, which you would expect of data, into
sub-clusters of juveniles, adult, female, male, disease, non-diseased,
and by different kinds of diseases.
Across species, there's a dimension in the model representation space where
Darwin's finches align by a beak size.
There is nothing that we gave the model about beak size, but clearly that
information is already contained in the images.
So there is a lot of biological information that's there that scientists have been
observing clearly, right? That has been noted a little bit over a century ago.
The fish, based on the FishAIR dataset, AI-ready
dataset,
is separating by freshwater and non-freshwater.
So scientists are starting to use that to start asking questions and
generating hypotheses. For example, one of the
image genomics evolutionary biologists is looking at this partition separation
between female and male in birds, and understanding the distance between female and
male, and the
sexual dimorphism by mating structure of the species, right?
You can ask many other questions, and I'll give you a few.
You can explore this space by looking,
sort of doing visual search, and giving it an example image, and asking what's
around it, right? So starting to see how the data are organized and what
does the model essentially think is like that, right?
What is the information in the images that's similar to that?
So in this case, it's a diseased milkweed, and you can see that all the other
images near it are of damaged milkweed. You can start asking about interactions.
Here is a moth pollinating
a flower, and it will give you around it are images of the same species of moth as
a pollinator for different plants.
So you can essentially visually ask the question, what does this moth pollinate?
And you can think of your own kind of queries.
So this is starting to fill some of the shortfalls, right?
Just by injecting a little bit of biological information into the
machine learning model. You can start asking questions about,
is this a new species, right? Flagging new species and speeding up the naming
of one of the most under-monitored, understudied, and
under-named taxonomic group, moths.
Right? So this is a project by David Rolnick at McGill University, who's part of
the ABC, AI and Biodiversity Change Global Center.
They built the whole, starting with a camera trap that attracts moths, the whole
processing system, and working with a Montreal insectarium to
start identifying new species using BioCLIP.
Sarah Beery, who already was mentioned and also is part of ABC,
took a different approach to surface different kinds of interactions with
iNaturalist data with the project Inquire. Right?
And they're now starting to look explicitly for interactions, trophic
interactions particularly.
But okay, great. This allows us to look at more things, but are we looking more
carefully? Are we understanding what we're looking at?
And so for that, the second requirement, so not just scientific, the AI for science
has to
be able to facilitate discovery. We're kind of getting there, but then it needs to
be interpretable. So how do we make AI interpretable?
And so there's a lot of development recently in the machine learning AI communities
on sort of pushing interpretability in different ways.
Of asking questions both from the model's perspective of what does model pay
attention to when making a determination that this
image belongs to this class of species.
We really took it and pushed it towards biologically meaningful interpretability.
So not just highlighting parts of the image that are relevant for the model,
but pushing it to the kind of modern machine learning models, transformers use
attention mechanisms to guide the model
in this billion parameter space towards a particular region of that space.
So these ones essentially after making a determination, ask, okay, what
parts of the image were relevant for this particular species?
We train the models to be essentially species identification experts
from the attention point of view. And so it highlights parts of the image, not as
an amorphous kind of cloud, but specifically from any pose, from any
position of the same species, this rose-breasted grosbeak, say that several times
fast. It highlights parts of the image, so in this case, the
white belly, the rose chest, the black head, and so on, right?
And so you can see that the position and the specific location matters.
Great. And you can do it again at any taxonomic...
Somewhere? No. Okay, great. Any taxonomic level. Great.
So it highlighted some part of the image. Awesome.
But what about that part of the image?
And so we used sparse autoencoders, which is yet another kind of
state-of-the-art set of tools that are broadly
now being used and developed within machine learning community, AI community, to
start associating the
machine learning features, dimensions of a space, with something that's
semantically biologically meaningful. Takes a lot of work, turns out.
So, okay, in this case, so we highlighted a beak.
What does it mean? Does it mean that birds have a beak and it's important?
Well, it's not a particularly deep discovery, right?
So essentially it highlights a beak when we ask a question, what makes this
bird, so house sparrow, North American house sparrow, different from other
birds? A beak? Well, not really, right? Like, what about the beak?
So we developed a set of tools where you can actually ask that question, what about
the beak? What about this particular part that is highlighted?
So you can essentially minimize the weight on every
pixel that's highlighted and say, "If I minimize the weight and
reconstruct this bird with these zeroed-out weights, what would it look like?"
Well, it turns out what it would look like, that beak would become smaller and
darker. Okay, great. So what if I jack up those weights and really make this
particular part the most important part of saying this is a house sparrow?
What makes this house sparrow different from all the other birds?
Well, it turns out this beak then becomes different shape.
It's thicker, bigger, and wider. So you can start asking not just it's a beak, but
what about the beak? And that leads to discovery of new traits.
We're starting also to work with biologists to
refresh or build new taxonomic keys, dichotomous keys.
Not taxonomic keys, dichotomous keys.
We're working on with lepidopterists to identify
distinguishing characteristics that are missed by humans for mimic
species that until now only have been possible through genome
sequencing,
identifying new species, and also correlating or associating
traits, and I'll talk a little bit, with functional traits or with ecological
factors. All right?
And that part, the last part, is in beetles.
So we're working with the National Ecological Observatory Network in the US, NEON,
to process their biological collections, particularly in this case, ground beetles.
This is bycatch. And the catch, so they're stored by a repository.
They're not imaged.
They are in these kinds of test tubes.
So we developed a pipeline, the workflow, that is common to many museums, in fact,
and other biological natural history collections, where you have your collection,
you need to image it, and you need to image in a way that actually also gives you a
lot of additional information and processes labels.
By the way, as an aside, if you're doing it for a herbarium or
botanical garden collection, Leaf Machine, and I've mentioned it a couple of times
yesterday, we're not part of the project, but Leaf Machine is a great workflow with
a lot of tools that speed up that process.
Okay, beetles. So,
take a test tube, dump it, process it, so all the tools, segment it,
get the outline of each segment, put landmarks, and measure the distances between
landmarks. Turns out, that way of doing it, when we just published this, is more
accurate than doing it with calipers.
So now you have this whole set of measurements and traits
that can start being correlated with different things, and start being
associated with function. Right.
One of the things,
the first pass of this, not to that level of resolution, but we ran a competition
together with our sister institutes of imageomics on a machine learning competition
of associating beetle communities as predictors for
drought
ahead of time.
And you can get some signal out of it, and now we're redoing the whole thing with
actual, very precise, these trait measures, distances, and other information,
because there is a reasonable hypothesis that
traits in ground beetles respond to soil moisture.
So there should be a signal, and so we're verifying, essentially, testing these
kinds of things, and others.
But wait. Behavior is also traits.
So what about behavioral traits at population level?
You need very different kind of data.
And so this is where we started working in Kenya, but also
expanded it to other locations, of using drones.
This is today the tool for behavior data collection of
populations at population scale, particularly about movement, but also developing
the whole workflow of
how do you collect that data, and also the computer vision workflows
of identifying different behavior.
There is
independent research at Max Planck Institute of animal behavior that is
expanding the vocabulary, the ontology of
animal behavior and the ecological kind of taxonomies and ecological
ontologies.
And so especially not just individual, but pair-wise.
So where we come in is how do you build systems, autonomous systems, that
can collect data on animal behavior in situ, in the wild, without actually
altering the very behavior that we want to collect?
And how do you do it as a system so where an acoustic
sensor can maybe detect behavior that sends the drone and so on?
And so with that, this work has been done by Jenna Klein, a wonderful PhD student,
who just graduated and is doing post-doc at MIT.
Will be on the market
as a faculty position market. So her paper on this won the Robert May prize as the
first non-biology paper that won that prize.
But relevantly for this community, she
started the Wild Labs Ed Computing working group and
is very interested in expanding the FAIR4AI drone data
standards, because that is now the primary source of animal behavior and movement
data.
And so her talk is on Thursday. She's going to give a remote talk on this on
Thursday,
if you're interested.
Overall, there's a whole bunch more tools that have been developed in genomics.
They're all open,
all the datasets are fair and FAIR4AI.
We're developing the standard, in fact, that I'll tell you in a little bit, and
they're all accessible there. There's a very well indexed and searchable, and
there's even a tool, part of it is a method for creating your own repository
and searchable catalog, so you can with your own branding.
So part of that, you can have your own method for doing it.
The other thing is, remember I told you at the beginning how machine learning
community thinks and gets mobilized to answer any question.
One of the things is benchmarks. And so benchmark is a well-defined task, plus
training and testing data. And so we realized that if we want to change the culture
and the way that machine learning methods are being developed for this community,
we need to change the benchmarks. And so we've released our own set of benchmarks
that are biologically relevant. And if you want to add to that, please come and
talk to me. We're already seeing externally kind of external, so movement
prediction benchmarks and others are starting to appear that are well-defined for
machine learning community, but the tasks and the
accuracy measurements, and all the other relevant ones are from biological
perspective.
If anybody has the answer to that, let's talk.
So,
right, with this, clearly, AI is about to replace humans and do science.
No. So just as a quick aside and to kind of calm everybody,
we've done a study. We started doing a study project on
selecting ecological papers that are very data-driven and
identifying questions in this paper, so as benchmarks,
that are answerable.
So it's paper that has a dataset, very data-driven, single dataset, one of those
four.
And the questions are of the kind, do distorted species exhibit large episodic
fluctuations in annual abundance in Sonoran Desert habitats, right?
So these are very well-posed, data-driven questions.
So we've collected right now, and been published, collected about 300 of those,
and building this dataset of benchmark questions and partitioned the scientific
process to answer these questions into four stages.
Here's the dataset source, let's say NEON, National Ecological Observatory Network.
Find the relevant data to answer this question within this...
We're being very, very nice. We're saying in this dataset, in the right database.
Once you've found it, figure a way to actually extract it.
You build the API to extract it, then organize the data, and then actually, okay,
this organized data, use this kind of analysis to answer this question.
So typically, it is that last one that is posed for AI agents,
because by this point, the scientists have already done all of the work.
And so we said, "Okay, let's get AI agents, state of the art at the time," so this
is four months ago, so state of the art has changed.
But still, AI agents, to answer all of this and run them through all four stages.
And so it turns out that, and compare them to a non-expert human,
also known as computer science graduate student,
to see how
they perform. And on the X-axis is the number of tokens measured in the dollar
signs that you need to answer that question. Right?
The more tokens you give, the better the answer, and so different agents also
require different amount of tokens to get to the answer.
We measure their pass rate as within 90% of the accurate
answer. So, it got 90% of the necessary data. That's a pass.
So,
there's a strong correlation. The more money you give them, the more tokens, the
better they figure out. But the surprising thing, they fail spectacularly to
construct the right API once they know what data to get.
And that is a statement about data readiness, not about the ability of AI agents,
right?
Also this, once you get the right data, prepare it for analysis.
That one actually is a statement of
the implicit knowledge and a statement of metadata
that describes the data that is not accessible.
There's a lot of implicit knowledge that's not accessible for AI agents.
I don't know if we want to make it accessible, but it's that that makes them fail.
Right, and once you actually specify, okay, here's the data, here's the analysis
method, ready, set, go, that's when AI agents can do it-ish, right?
To about 60% accuracy, but also with thousands of dollars worth of
tokens. I'd rather train a graduate student to do that, honestly.
But the thing is, this failure kind of mode is very much
about the
AI readiness of data. Because there is no AI without data.
We finally get to this point in the talk.
And a lot of other resources.
But especially for data, so we do need, as David pointed out, we do need
distributed data infrastructure that supports AI use directly if we want to
use AI methods
to answer them. And that also respects the rights and
provides value for the primary data collectors.
GBIF is not a primary data collector, despite the fact that's where we get data to
build big models. And so we started thinking about what does AI ready mean and came
to the conclusion that
AI ready is very specific to a question.
But in between lives FAIR4AI, which is findable, accessible, interoperable, and
reusable by a machine, by something that's automatically accessible,
right? And then you can get that and make it very specific for a task, AI-ready.
And so we're thinking about it as this question data model triangle,
where increasingly when you have a question or a scientific question or a research
and management kind of
decision,
you need data and you need methods, right, as we saw in this workflow.
And we're starting to see this is where LLMs do come in.
You can translate them into requirements.
To answer this question, I need this kind of data, not this specific data, but this
kind of data, and maybe this kind of analysis.
And models particularly are really good at being documented because we now have
model cards, we now have model context protocols that kind of expose to the rest of
the world, I need this kind of data. I work with this kind of...
I can answer potentially this kind of questions, well-defined questions.
So there's still not a direct connection here.
But data,
so there are now emerging standards that are being developed of FAIR, FAIR4AI,
FAIR4ML
Beyond the biodiversity community,
there's still a lot of work to do. We're still arguing about the
definitions. And also, to build these models, they're built on aggregate data
like GBIF,
where a lot of data coming into that comes from primary small data
collectors, primary data sources, small projects, small conservation
organizations in case of biodiversity, regional governments, and so on.
And so all of it flows uni-directionally towards these big aggregators.
And
there is very little at the moment of even infrastructure that
brings value back to the primary data collectors.
And so there is a new white paper and a framework put together, so this comes out
of Latin America and the Caribbean, on sovereign data supply chain.
Of what it means and how to operationalize it,
and what are the requirements. I highly encourage you to take a look at this.
And so
we've created, the group led by
Eric Sokol of NEON, Alex Wild of Smithsonian Institution,
Elizabeth Compagno, Hilmar Lapp, and others,
has developed this FAIR for AI checklist,
which
specifically identifies criteria in these four categories and develops them
into much, much more structured... Four, three, two, five.
Okay, I'll take bids.
Okay. And it kind of expands it into different
categories. We now have more than 90 categories
of FAIR for AI, so clearly it's not a human task. So what do we do?
We developed an agent
that does this. It's an agent that goes through this task list and sort of with--
This whole thing has been developed in three workshops.
Community workshops, international community workshops, but also started with GBIF,
iNat, NatureServe,
and kind of bigger ones, and then expanded it.
We had a workshop at Living Data, we had a workshop at the First International
Conservation Technology Conference, so kind of building this with the community.
What does it mean? What's important? How do we check it?
Do the agents, when they return an answer, that also is constructive, not just a
score, but tells you here's why, what you need to bring up that score, do they
actually help?
Do they give what we think they should be giving as an answer?
So we ran it on the initial data sets that are part of this working group.
And if you want to know more, again, there is a Thursday talk.
Eric Sokol was supposed to deliver it. I'm going to speak in his place.
But it is the work that is done by this group.
And so to kind of expand this, why do we care?
Because as I showed you, we're getting a lot more data.
And the future is multi-scale,
multi-sensory, and multi-modal.
And so we're starting to get data sets that are going across scales and modalities.
One of the first multi-scale data sets was the OpenForis data set that goes from
individual tree data all the way to planetary forest data.
That's because trees don't walk away, so, you know.
And you can see them from satellites, so that's wonderful.
But we're seeing that data, that kind of data, multi-scale.
How do we build data infrastructure and standards that actually
capture that? That connect that, and that make it possible for machine
learning methods, not just to analyze, but to provide value back to the
original data providers. When we identify the canopy, it should go all the way back
to the primary source, not just to aggregate.
When we do it across different modalities and connect different modalities, again,
what does it mean to align data and to provide value and to give an answer?
And so we started with a small experiment at a safari in North America.
It's the largest safari in North America, The Wilds.
That is an hour from my university.
By instrumenting with everything that we could get our hands on at the time.
And
so that we can start looking at this, both from the systems perspective, the
computational perspective, and also data perspective.
And that talk and how do we think about it is also on Thursday.
I'm going to be busy on Thursday, but this is work done by Jenna Klein, and I'll be
presenting it.
And
that, so that we can actually start moving from just using AI to
speed up and scale up data collection and processing and naming things,
even though we need that, to actually generating hypotheses,
understanding systems, and predicting how these systems would behave under unseen
conditions. And with that,
all of this, I may be standing here, but the work is done by everybody else pretty
much, but me. So thank you.
There's no questions, right?
We're going to find out.
Oh.
So I know that it is break time, but is there one question that we can give Tanya?
It's got to be the best question that you've got.
No pressure, no pressure.
No pressure.
But also, I will be available to talk-
She will be here-
For the whole week
... she'll be here all week, yeah.
Yeah, I'll be around. But I am happy to answer questions.
Oh yeah, there is a question.
All the way in the back.
So is it out? Maybe make sense.
Wait for the microphone. Hold on, we have people online.
Yeah.
Do you think you could expand the BioClip model to paleo collections and use a
similar approach, and have you looked at that?
Great question. So paleo collections, yes.
In fact, some of the GBIF already has paleo.
Not quite paleo-paleo, but it has bones and skeletal information.
So the answer is probably yes. But we would need--
There's no AI without data.
And there are efforts now to explicitly do this specifically for paleo collections
because there are a lot of these
nuances there of you have one tooth, what do you do with it?
What kind of information are you getting out of it?
And so it is very much multimodal. So there is the
3D image, quite often more so than 2D, but 3D DNA chemical
information. So the models that are being trained for paleo are a
little bit different. But there's certainly a connection that's possible there,
yeah.
Another question here.
Yeah.
Yeah, quick question, hopefully. I'm not sure if I get to run.
I'm not judging.
I heard that, yeah, it sounded a little bit to me that you also criticize the
deployment way of the data sets at the end with regard to quality.
So if they go to Kaggle or wherever, OpenML, they might sink into
the trash, which is already there, which has questionable taxonomic names in it and
so on. So you mentioned FAIR4ML, which is for the models, not for the data itself,
but this is published in a qualitative repository, to my knowledge.
It's ML entry, as I've been made, and maybe it's also in Alexidom now.
So do you envision something similar for highly curated biological or biodiversity
data sets for deployment?
Yeah. So just to understand the question, because there's the preamble to the
question, then in the question.
So is the question about FAIR4ML?
How do you, sorry?
Envision to deploy the data sets, where should they go in?
Should they end in cargo, for example, as repository to mobilize them there, where
they might undergo on the trash? If you follow up these all adding to Croissant
standards, high level, add provenance, Swiss prof or whatever, and so on.
So where do you think could these data set lives in and be mobilized for the
community? Will this be still the standard repositories, which have the highest
success, of course?
So there are a couple of ways of
going about sort of adding the FAIR4AI or FAIR4ML metadata as it's being
accumulated. Right? So
one way, which we're hoping, is that
the aggregate, the big data sets, the
aggregates like NEON, like GBIF, and INA, we actually make those
FAIR4AI, not FAIR4ML. There's a distinction.
So FAIR4AI, and by the way, that started with the Ecological Synthesis Center, ESO,
FAIR4AI checklist, and also augmented with a
human health checklist and a disease checklist.
And so there's kind of developing and community input.
So that is a property of the data set, and
that all of the annotation that happens is on the original data set.
Right. That's one thing. The thing is, once it goes FAIR4ML and model
ready, these kinds of data sets are being published now in machine learning
communities, and they lose connection to the primary data at this point.
And there is no, quite often, even attribution anymore to primary data.
So we're actually trying to break this.
And
so CyVerse and other projects, more broadly than biodiversity data, are really
figuring out how do you keep provenance chains, and everything
that's created by machine learning methods.
So for example, if I put bounding box around every beetle, the coordinates of that
bounding box should go back to the original data provider, right, on the same
image. When we de-duplicate
GBIF data, because there are a lot of duplicates there or near duplicates,
that information should go back to the primary data providers.
When we clean up and
reconnect to taxonomy, because GBIF just changed its taxonomy service, right?
So we have to update. If somebody's going to use it for machine learning
training of any kind, the name has to be the most recent.
But you also have to have connections to the original ones, right, and
all the versions of the name so that you know what to associate with.
And so we've built ways to do these connections on GBIF data.
And it is now going to be part of GBIF, but it also has to go back to the original
data providers so they can derive value from the work that we've done, which is a
lot of work, and also not to have to use AI
resources, cyber infrastructure resources, to redo that work, which they probably
can't even do because you need to do it in the context of a big data set.
And so the goal is not to create new repositories of any kind,
but to create a data infrastructure that amends existing one and create kind of
a relatively lightweight AI-enabled and AI-ready infrastructure on top of it
that brings value all the way up and down the data chain.
All right, so if there are additional questions, please find Tania at the break or
sometime during the week. I'm making an executive decision to give you a little
extra time for your break, especially since you'll have to travel a little bit to
get to the restrooms and come back. We will start promptly at 11:05.
So please, thank you for joining us.
Thank you, Tania, and we'll see you at 11:05.